Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 1 -- Letters to Franklin 1730-1776 Mss.B.F85inventory01
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 August 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Tucker, Henry. Bermuda
    Thanking Franklin on behalf of himself and also of their four deputies for presenting their Address to Congress; hopes they will obtain their reasonable request. Will endeavor to secure for America Whatever powder comes to Bermuda. Reasons for the law passed in Bermuda to prohibit the exportation of provisions. Greatly shocked on hearing of the terrible carnage in the late battle; hopes some expedient will be found to prevent further bloodshed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Howard, Martin Jr. Newbern
    Concerning a debt of his to Franklin which, owing to bad times, he is unable to pay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 August 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Bromfield, Thomas. London
    The Ministry still seem determined to pursue rigorous measures; more troops and men-of-war are going over; believes it to be impracticable to force these measures by the sword; results to be expected from the stoppage in the trade to America. Since the battle of June 7th their reproach of cowardice, however, is wiped off. Death of their friend. [Josiah] Quincy [Jr.]
    Printed in Penna. Magazine of Hist. and Biog, XXVII, 162.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 August 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William. Perth Amboy
    Enclosing a copy of Mr. George Morgan's letter on the subject of the Indian grant of land (see IV, 62) with his answer thereto; would be glad of Franklin's opinion respecting the contents. Read Messrs. Walpole and Sargent's letter to Franklin; thinks it impossible to keep such transactions as secrect as they deem necessary. Discusses business of Major Trent and Mr. Tilghman.
    Printed in Penna, Magazine of Hist. and Biog, XXVII, 163.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 September 6; A.L.S. 4p.; Strahan, William. London
    Takes expection to Franklin's remark, — "all tends to a separation." Represents the evil consequences to America of a break with England; enumerates the many past privileges enjoyed by the Colonies; terrible evils of war; hopes on the reassembling of Parliament something may be found to stop the progress of such an unnatural and destructive quarrel. In the Declaration of Congress he sees" that foreign assistance, if necessary, is undoubtedly attainable"; supposes this is merely a threat; evils of foreign interference. Probable suffering in store for America. Comments on the last petition of Congress to Great Britain. Prophcsics future trouble from the arming of the provincials.
    Printed in Penna. Magazine of Hist. and Biog, XXVII, 165.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 September 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William. Perth Amboy
    Enclosing a copy of the exposition of the Resolution of the House of Commons and also the minutes of the two last sessions of the New Jersey Assembly, containing his remarks on the present unnatural dispute between Great Britain and her colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 September 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Foxcroft, John. New York
    Received a most friendly and polite letter from their mutual friend, Lord Le Despencer, who approves of every step he (Foxcroft) has taken in these troublesome times. Hears that some people have had the curiosity to pry into his correspondence with Franklin. Encloses His Majesty's answer to the City Address.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 October 21; A.L.S. W[illia]m Govett, Secretary. 1p.; The Committee of Safety of Pennsylvania. Philadelphia
    Meeting of the Committee of Safety and of the Committee of Assembly, also of the Board at which the appointment of a commodore will be considered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 November 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Horatio. Head Q'rs
    Giving accounts of the capture of several vessels with cargoes of wine, dry goods, rum, sugar and fruit respectively; evident that "wine and punch will not be wanting to the Sons of Liberty." Asks how the pulse of the politicians is beating. Cannot write for interruptions; no peace possible for him until he gives the ambassador from Marblehead two barrels of powder for the defense of that port.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 November 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Greene, William. Westerly [R. I.]
    Acknowkedging Franklin's favor from New Haven. At a loss to express his gratitude to Franklin for taking his little son under his care; consults him as to the best means of making him a useful member of society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 November 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Greene, Caty. Westerly [R. I.]
    Cannot express how pleased she is to have her boy with Franklin; hopes he may deserve such goodness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 November 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Stevenson, Margaret. Northumberland Court
    Expressing the deepest devotion to Franklin and mentioning all the friends who come to her house to talk of him and lament his absence. Mr. Strahan sorry to differ from Franklin, but it is a matter of principle. Does not know if he will ever get this letter; expects it will be opened, but is sure they will be puzzled to decipher it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Gates, Horatio. Headquarters
    News received of the capture of Quebec by their troops, assisted by 6000 Canadians. Burgoyne sails for London that very day; thinks if there is an honest mob left in London he and Gage cannot ride the streets in safety. Franklin will hear in Congress of their success at sea. Insists upon the condemnation of the Glasgow ship; every tittle of clothing on board needed for the soldiers. Trouble in retaining the Connecticut troops. Anxiously awaiting the results of the committe sent to Montreal; wishes Franklin could have been one of them. Splendid conduct of Gen. Montgomery and Col. Arnold. A play-house established in Boston, which opened with a tragedy; very possible it may conclude with one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Horatio. Headquarters
    Enclosing a copy of General Lee's letter lately sent to Gen. Burgoyne, if Franklin approves it may be published in the newspapers. Longs to send him his and Lee's opinions of the military measures to be pursued in Canada. Deprecates so much wrangling about forms of government; let them first establish their freedom; let them not tarnish the glorious and successful Continental arms by timid conduct; Franklin does not need these arguments; they are for certain others.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Lee, Charles. Camp
    Concerning the publishing of his letter to Gen. Burgoyne. A good deal surprised and a little shocked at the proceedings of the Assembly; Considers the "injunction of these gentlemen to their delegates to dissent from any resolve leading to independence ill-timed, impertinent and impolitic"; bad results to be expected from such a declaration. Wishes Franklin would send some man who has the reputation of being a soldier to Virginia,which is the weak point; explains the prejudice of the common people against any man who has not seen service; cites anecdote to prove their blind faith in the latter. Enlistments go on swimmingly; let them but get powder and Boston shall be theirs.
    Printed in Journal of Military Service Institution, July, 1903, p.72.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Hewson, Mary. Kensington
    Her mother [Mrs. Stevenson] not very well; describes the various attractions of her children; her son William struggling with the difficulties of orthography, which she begs Franklin as the future sovereign and law-giver in the empire of America to render less difficult. Rails against the present fashion of small waists; longs to be in America where she may appear without distortion; comments on the extravagant manner of dressing the hair. Concerning a number of sheep and hogs which are to be sent to Boston to feed — the fishes, she hopes. Lady Blunt has a son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Mead, Catharine. Sunsbury Penna
    Is the daughter of John Croker and was once at Franklin's house when she was little; is at least a head taller since the receipt of Franklin's letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 23; L. 1p.; [Wharton, Samuel]. London
    Introducing Mr.Wrixon, a gentleman of character and connections in Ireland, to Franklin's friendship, civility and protection; as his late publications will show, he has not been an indifferent spectator of the present unhappy dispute. Dares not say a word on public affairs; he will hear all about them from the bearer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 23; A.L. 3p.; Bancroft, Edward. London
    Recomends Mr. Wrixon, a young man possessing valuable military knowledge to Dr. Franklin's friendly acquaintance and assistance. Wishes to refrain from discussing politics through the mail. Lord Howe anxious to restore peace with America; has gone to the country to see whether the Ministers can gratify his demands respecting the marines and extend his powers.
    (Signature torn out.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1775 December 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Gilpin, Israel. Wilmington
    Informed by his kinsman, George Gilpin, that several of the manufacturers are likely to suffer from want to coal; mentions various places where he thinks coal could be found.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1774; L. 1p.; Cushing, Thomas
    The exportation of gun powder or any sort of arms or ammunition prohibited by order of the King. The Colonies apprehend that this forebodes the most vigorous exertion of martial force and are adopting the most effective measures to defend themselves. Military stores in Rhode Island and New Hampshire removed to places of safety.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1775 ?]; A.L.S. 3p.; Lee, Charles
    Suggestions as to the best measures to be taken to prepare for war with Great Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 February 24; D.S. J[onathan] B. Smith, Secretary. 1p.; Committee of the Pennsylvania Assembly
    Appointing a deputation to request Dr. Franklin to take his seat in the House, if consistent with his other duties. If not, that he would be pleased to resign that another Burgess may be elected.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 February 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Priestley, Joseph. London
    Dr. Price's pamphlet. Conduct of the Ministry. Philosophical experiments. Fixed air.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 171). also in Penna-Magazine of Hist. and Biog., XXVII, 169.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 February 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Goforth, Capt William. Three Rivers Canada
    Poverty and distress of the people in that province; afraid to join with either side; his opinion as to the best measures to be adopted. Anxious as commander of Three Rivers to know what forces are coming to his assistance; neglect of the Northern Department.
    Printed in Journal of Military Service Institution, July, 1903, P.74.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 February 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Horatio. Headquarters
    Introducing Baron de Woedtke; his tyrannical treatment by the King of Prussia; hopes America may continue to embrace with her wonted cordiality every oppressed subject from every quarter of the globe. Convinced that the enemy intend to commence their operations from New York.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 February 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Hartley, David. London
    Urging measures of reconciliation between Great Britain and the Colonies.
    Printed in Penna. Magazine of Hist. and Biog., XXVII, 171.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 March 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Agreeable to Franklin's desire, encloses his account.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 [March 21]; A.L.S. 2p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    British have left Boston in disgrace before the Colonial forces. Most of them just sailed this morning; where to is a secret. Our bombardment was unexpected, and the occupation of Dorchester Hill completed their consternation. Boston stands, but is much plundered. His own house looted. "Common Sense" is eagerly read and greatly admired. Colonies cannot be subdued by force.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1776 March 20]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Rush, Dr Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Mentioning the hour when the members of the Canadian Committee will wait on him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 March 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Barclay, David. London
    Persuaded that it will not be for want of inclination in Lord Howe should the olive branch not rise superior to the din of war.
    Printed in Penna. Magazine of Hist. and Biog, XXVII, 175.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 May 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Hazard, Eben. New York
    The "Roebuck," of 44 guns, on shore on the east bank of the Brandy-wine; eight row galleys, the Province ship and "Reprisal" have gone down to take her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 May 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    Consternation caused by the firing of the alarm guns, on account of three men-of-war which were descried coming up the bay. The "Roe-buck" got off without sustaining any damages. Franklin will see by the papers what a formidable armament to expect; 45,000 commissioners at least, of various nations, commanded by Lord Howe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Richard. Philadelphia
    The action between their armed boats and His Majesty's ship, the "Roebuck," of 44 guns, and "Liverpool," of 28 guns, off Wilmington; the latter got a severe drubbing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 May 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Washington, Gen George. New York
    Transmits enclosed letter, the others he received with this he forwarded to Congress. On the 17th received news of our troops being obliged to raise the siege of Quebec, with the loss of their cannon, a number of small arms, provisions, etc. Had hoped that the troops would maintain their position and, on the arrival of the two brigades detached from hence, consisting of ten regiments, our blockade, bravely kept up for a long time by a handful of men, would terminate in the reduction of Quebec and our consequent possession of the important country of which it belongs. Regrets its effect on his mission in that country.
    [S. torn out.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1776. May.]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hazard, Eben
    Will watch the sloops from Albany and forward the Doctor's bedding as soon as it comes to hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 June 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Prichard, William. Philadelphia
    Has applied to several printers for work, but in vain. Begs Franklin to allow him the use of his types and press for a short time, as he is offered the printing of several small things; promises to return them whenever required and to pay their use.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Killceys, Lois
    Reminding him of their ancient friendship. Recommends [name illegible] to Franklin's notice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1776.] June 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
    Sending Franklin the three volumes entrusted to his care by M. [Barbeu] Dubourg, and a present of books from himself. Gave Franklin's letter to Mr. Rush. Outside of the Members of Congress, wishes to keep his communications secret.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1776. June]?; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Jefferson, Thomas.
    Encloses a paper which, with some small alterations, has been approved by the Committee; asks him to peruse it and suggest such alterations as his more enlarged view of the subject will dictate. The paper has been returned to him to change a particular sentiment or two. He proposes to lay it again before the Committee [to draft a Declaration of Independence?].
  - to Benjamin Franklin and the other Delegates of the Province of Pennsylvania in Congress., 1776 July 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, Thomas. Crown Point
    Detailing the losses of the sixth battalion of Pennsylvania in the engagement near Three Rivers. Account of a small party of officers and men being surprised while fishing, by the Indians; two of the party murdered and inhumanly scalped, the rest, with two exceptions, made prisoners. Begs them to think of some plan whereby these men may be exchanged. It is the wish of the army that Gen. Thompson should be restored to them immediately.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 3; A.L.S. 8p.; Woedtke, Frederick William, Baron de. Crown Point
    Account of his march to Sorel. Council of war with Generals Arnold and Thompson; opposition on his part to their plan of quitting Sorel; prevented Col. de Haas from pitching two of their cannon into the water in his desire to precipitate their march. Council of War called at St. John, where it was decided to cross Lake Champlain. Arrival at Crown Point; neglect of hospitals; bad food. Has many enemies, — all Tories. Anxious to do honor to Franklin's recommendation, but fears they will not be able to hold Crown Point.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 4; A.L.S. 3p.; de Woedtke, Frederick William Baron. Crown Point
    Their difficult situation; need of experienced soldiers. Criticizes Generals Arnold and Sullivan; considers the latter ignorant of his profession. Does all in his power for the well-being of his troops. Heard at Chambly that the English had offered 500 guineas for his capture; naturally much flattered. Begs him to give the position of aide-de-camp general to an experienced man; recommends Col. St. Clair(?). The four vessels of war on the lake in very bad condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Lawrence, John and William Smith. Burlington
    Informing him that Mrs. Mecom's Benjamin husband is at times very dangerous, being often deprived of his reason; asks Franklin's help in placing him in the hospital at Philadelphia, or in confining him in some other way.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    Introducing M. de Converez, a great traveler who has seen and knows a country at present the object of so much attention in Europe; asks Franklin's assistance in procuring for M. de Converez a proper settlement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
    Works hard to render himself worthy of Franklin's recommendation and esteem. Advice he gave Gen. Mercer about the necessity of guarding the Jersey coast. Concerning a plan for defending the coast of America which he has submitted to Mr. Hancock. Account of small engagements between their batteries and the enemy's boats; fine behaviour of the soldiers. Begs Franklin to plead with Congress for slowness in counsel and swiftness in action.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Wayne, Anthony. Ticonderoga
    So far removed from the seat of government that very little intelligence reaches them. Informed that Lord Howe has joined the General before New York; expresses certain fears for the brave and generous sons of America. In high expectation of shortly seeing Burgoyne; he will find an enemy small in number yet brave by nature and longing to revenge the unfortunate affair at Three Rivers. Account of the troops under Col. St. Clair and himself. Strength of their naval force as compared with the enemy. His soldiers destitute of almost very necessary — shoes, stockings, shirts and soap — essential articles in an army; pleads for some method of sending on these things.
    Printed in Journal of Military Service Instituion, July, 1903. p.76.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Woedtke, Frederick William, Baron de. Crown Point
    Their difficult situation; need of experienced soldiers. Criticizes Generals Arnold and sullivan; considers the latter ignorant of his profession. Does all in his power for the well-being of his troops. Heard at Chambly that the English had offered 500 guineas for his capture; naturally much flattered. Begs him to give the position of aide-de-camp general to an experienced man; recommends Col. St. Clair(?). The four vessels of war on the lake in very bad condition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 19; A.L.S. 2p.; J.M. Lawrence and William Smith
    Informing him that Mrs. Mecom's Benjamin husband is at times very dangerous, being often deprived of his reason; asks Franklin's help in placing him in the hospital at philadelphia, or in confining him in some other way.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 26; A.L.S. 4p.; Kermorvan, Chevalier de
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 July 31.; A.L.S. 3p.; Wayne, Anthony. Ticonderoga
    So far removed from the seat of government that very little intelligence reaches them. Informed that Lord Howe has joined the General before New York; expresses certain fears for the brave and generous sons of America. In high expectation of shortly seeing Burgoyne; hewill find an enemy small in number yet brave by nature and longing to revenge the unfortunate affair at Three Rivers. Account of the troops under Col. St. Clair and himself. Strength of their naval force as compared with the enemy. His soldiers destitute of almost very necessary—shoes, stockings, shirts and soap—essential articles in an army; pleads for some method of sending on these things.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Goll, Le Président de. Montbeillard
    Asking Franklin to interest himself in Geo. Leopold Besson, bourgeois of MontbC)ilard, originally of Switzerland; his honesty and his misfortunes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Greene, Ray. Warwick R. I
    Acknowledging the many obligations he is under to Franklin; had a pleasant journey home; his relations and friends thought him much altered; concluded from their smiles that it was for the better. [Enclosure to Grandma Mecom.] Expressing a high sense of her goodness to him; out of his power to return it; hopes she will be pleased with Cousin Jenny's match, which they tell him is to be one, as he comes pretty often.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Dunlap, William. King and Queen
    Has just received a distressing letter from his son Ben informing him that the unknown benefactor who has contributed to his education so far, can do so no longer and that he must shift for himself; asks Franklin to take the poor boy under his partonage and so encourage his ardent thirst for knowledge and save him from the plough or spade. Gives an account of the other members of his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Newland, Mehetable. Stafford, Monmouth Co. N. J
    Asking whether he has heard anything of Mr. Newland since he embarked from New York for Quebec; from the different reports of the success of their troops at that place is under the greatest uneasiness for his welfare.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple. Philadelphia
    Arrived in Philadelphia after spending a night at Mr. and Mrs. Duffield's and waiting on Mr. Galloway. Mrs. Bache's son William very well. According to his Aunt Mecom's request, waited on Mrs. Van Vordice. Mrs. Turner and her husband in London, the latter to have a commission in the Guards.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Washington, George. New York
    Encloses a letter from Lord Howe, sent out by a flag the day before; with it comes a letter for Lieut. Barrington, who, if not among those who broke parole and went off to Canada, is in York, Pennsylvania.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Read, J. K. Williamsburg
    Though belonging to branch of the family so far removed from Franklin, has always retained an affection for him and would like much to hear sometimes from him. Recommending Col. Read, who commands the 1st regiment on its march to New York, and also Dr. Skinner, a gentleman eminent in his profession.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1776 August 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Ross, George. New York